A recent detailed study shows remarkable
images of tumors shrinking to nothing
after eliminating two amino acids from
our diet. Within that study, they not
only uncovered some of the mechanisms,
but they ran a clinical trial. So, a
study in humans showing these results to
hold up. Now, even with all this
excitement and brilliant science,
there's a lot of context to apply here.
These two amino acids are serene and
glycine. And in this image comes from a
person dealing with cancer. In fact
quite advanced cancer usually solid
tumors that were stage three or higher
grade. Now before the trial you can
clearly see that the tumor in the
intestinal tract and only 9 weeks later
the tumor has just about evaporated
completely. Now the reason this protocol
that people were placed on including
this serarine and glycine restriction.
So the image comes from colurectal
cancer and about half of the patients in
the study had colorectal cancer but
others had esophageal gastric liver and
other forms of cancer. In fact when
looking at a mouse model designed to
show how reproducible these results are
we can see that the glycine and serarine
restriction led to significant reduction
in tumor weight indicated by the red
bars. Now the reason for this effect
caused by glycine and serarine
restriction comes down to our immune
system. When researchers removed
particular immune cells from the body,
they discovered that serarine and
glycine restriction was still effective
unless a particular class of cells was
removed. Those cells are called CD8
positive cells. They're a type of T-
cell, a specialized immune cell that's
responsible for recognizing and
attacking what it is, what it has been
trained to attack. Hence their full
name, a cytotoxic TE-C cell. So the key
takeaway here is that serereine and
glycine restriction works through these
CD8 positive cytotoxic tea cells to
attack cancer cells making up the tumor.
Now to be clear, serarine and glycine
restriction are not sufficient to
completely stress and kill the cancer
cells. However, what it does is force
the cancer cells to rely on a specific
immune evasion technique to avoid death.
In doing so, we can then apply
imunotherapy that targets that specific
evasion technique, giving the cancer
cells very few options to escape. It's
like the cancer cell is running down a
side alley trying to escape the immune
cell police or something along those
lines and then it realizes there's a
dead end with no way out. It's pretty
remarkable. So what participants of this
clinical trial did was undergo cycles of
glycine and serarine restriction plus
amunotherapy. They would restrict both
amino acids for 9 weeks having their
blood metrics checked every 3 weeks.
Then they consumed a supplied diet
devoid of serarine and glycine and were
allowed to eat some fruits and
vegetables but nothing containing
appreciable amounts of either amino
acid. They were not put on a
calorierestricted diet and were given
enough nutrition to mostly maintain
their weight. So around 30 kilo calories
per kilogram of weight and 1.5 g of
protein per kilogram of weight. So, if a
person weighed 100 kg, that would be a
healthy 3,000 kilo calories per day and
150 g of protein. Now, while I teased
this one image of this tumor
disappearing, it does it actually
doesn't give us a full picture. So, here
we have all the patients numbered on the
horizontal axis. The zero there
indicates no change in tumor size. So
any bars that fall below that imaginary
line indicates a shrinking of the
tumors. Anything above indicates an
increase in size. We'll address that
shortly. This graph actually shows us
similar things in two ways. The way that
I just described it with the direction
of the bars, but they also categorize
based on clinical definitions where
people would slot. As clinical
definitions are strict and depend on
specific thresholds. Don't be fooled by
uh many being in the blue which is
associated with stable disease as
opposed to partial response meaning that
clinically defined reduction in tumor.
The key takeaway here is most people
experienced reductions in tumors and a
small number experienced an increase in
tumor size when using the serarine and
glycine deficient diet. Okay. So then
why why would most cancers show
improvements and some show worsening?
There's actually a good reason which
I'll get into and before that there's
something that the tumors do in response
to glycine and serin restriction in an
attempt to get around the issues caused
by this restriction. It's called
lactillation. In addition, there's a
dance between two proteins on the cell
surface PDL1 and PD1 that holds the key
to how tumors evade. and then eventually
fall to the treatments that we're
talking about here. I'm covering all
that in more detail and more than even
what I just said there in the extended
version of this video that you're
watching. If you're interested in
getting a complete breakdown of the
science, you access all my work, video,
article, podcast format, and much more
by joining the Physionic Insiders, which
is my premium research platform and
community. Link to join is in the
description. and I'd really love to have
you aboard. Now, the reason some people
still experience progression of cancer
could be down to a few possibilities.
One, the type of cancer. Remember, while
most cancers were colctyl, not all were,
which means that some cancers may be
immune to these effects. Alternatively,
this diet was used for 9 weeks, but was
run in 3 week cycles with data collected
during that time. Some patients stuck it
out for the full nine weeks. Others did
only one cycle, so three weeks. So, some
did in between. Interestingly, those
that stuck to it the longest tended to
experience tumor stabilization or
shrinkage. The relationship wasn't
perfect, though, and it's still
speculation, but there may be something
to the like time of exposure. The final
thing that I'll note on this is that
this was a phase one clinical trial. So
we don't have a comparison group. That
means that although some people
experience progression in their disease,
we don't know if they might have
experienced even greater or quicker
progression if they were not exposed to
this protocol. Still, clearly this helps
some people more than others within the
same treatment. The exact reasons aren't
known. So where does that land us
applicably? On one hand, the data is
heavy-handed toward human research,
which is great because it translates
from our genetically furry cousins to
our less furry selves. However, it is an
early small trial in a mixed group of
cancers and has no control group. So
while yes it is feasible to do something
like this over time because neither
glycine nor serarine are essential amino
acids, there are many many foods that
contain them. These patients were lucky
or unlucky depending on how much you
enjoy food to have specialized nutrition
created for them with this glycine and
searing extracted. It's tough to
eliminate glycine and searing entirely
though certainly possible to reduce it.
This seems more so something that needs
to be designed for this special use case
of cancer. Also, I realize that some
people supplement with amino acids like
glycine that there's even evidence of
glycine helping fight cancer. So, it
might be confusing to run across studies
showing this restriction is beneficial
in fighting cancer. That's a nuance
conversation that I can get into at
another time, but the short of it is
that cancer is a difficult disease to
pin down. Different cancers respond
differently to the same treatment in
some cancers. So glycine may be
effective while for others it may be
detrimental. We just don't have that
enough data to tease that out or at
least those distinctions. But rest
assured there is nothing here that
indicates that a person who is healthy
as in not diagnosed with cancer should
now limit their glycine consumption. I'm
focusing on glycine because that's what
I've been looking at in greater depth
but the same may be true for Siri. So
this is something to keep an eye on for
the future and it would be a remarkable
way to reverse cancers if we can figure
out all the details. Still this is an
excellent first stab at it. In the end
we can say a few things. One that
glycine and serarine restriction allows
our immune system especially cytotoxic
tea cells to attack and destroy cancer
cells. In humans this is paired with
specific imunotherapy that facilitates
that process. Two, there is now early
evidence in humans that this protocol
directly leads to slowing or reversing
of cancer in most people studied. Much
more data is needed. However, beyond
amino acid restriction, there's also
other molecules, vitamins in fact, that
have been believed for decades to kill
cancer as well. I cover those studies
right here. Thanks for tuning in. What
incredible early research. I'll see you
in the next one. Bye.